OK.
네.
Today, we'll be talking about different tasks of core Computer
오늘은 core Computer Vision의 여러 task들,
Vision, algorithms and tasks, detection and segmentation.
즉 알고리즘과 task들, detection과 segmentation에 대해
We will also be covering topics around visualization
이야기할 것입니다. 그리고 visualization과
and understanding.
understanding에 관한 주제도 다룰 예정입니다.
I will cover the most important ones.
가장 중요한 내용들을 다루도록 하겠습니다.
Like the previous lecture last time,
지난 시간, 즉 저번 강의에서
what we discussed was around the topic of transitioning
우리가 이야기했던 주제는 sequence to sequence model에서
from sequence to sequence models, RNNs to transformers.
RNN에서 transformer로의 전환에 관한 것이었습니다.
And we saw that transformers were
그리고 transformer는
defined by having some encoder, a number of layers,
어떤 encoder를 가지고 있고, 여러 개의 layer가 있으며,
which had multi-headed, self-attention, and layer norm,
그 layer들은 multi-headed self-attention과 layer norm,
as well as some MLP layers.
그리고 MLP layer들로 구성되어 있다는 것을 보았습니다.
And this was, ultimately, called something
그리고 이것은 결국
that we now refer to as encoder encoding the sequence.
지금 우리가 sequence를 encoding하는 encoder라고 부르는
And then if we need to decode an image or a language, a sequence
어떤 것으로 정의되었습니다. 그리고 만약 이미지나 언어 같은
as the output, then similar type of architecture
sequence를 출력으로 decode해야 한다면, 비슷한 종류의
is used for decoder getting the encoder tokens as input,
architecture가 decoder에도 사용되는데, encoder token들을
taking those as input, and then generating what is--
input으로 받아서, 그것을 input으로 취한 뒤 우리가
I'm hoping that you can see my cursor too,
원하는 output을 생성합니다. 제 커서도 보이시길 바랍니다.
what is the desired output.
원하는 output을 생성하는 것이죠.
We did talk--
우리는 이야기했습니다--
Justin talked quite extensively about the differences
Justin이 sequence를 모델링하는 방식들의 차이에 대해
of modeling sequences, recurrent neural networks, RNNs,
꽤 자세히 이야기했었죠, recurrent neural network, RNN,
and their variations that we've talked last week,
그리고 지난주, 아마 화요일에 이야기했던 그 변형들에 대해서요,
I think, on Tuesday about and then using convolution also as
그리고 또 다른 접근법으로 convolution을 사용하는 것에 대해서도요.
another approach.
그 이야기도 했었습니다.
But we talked about, ultimately, that self-attention
하지만 결국 우리가 이야기한 것은 오늘날 많은 application에서
is what we work with in many of the applications these days.
우리가 실제로 사용하는 것은 self-attention이라는 것이었습니다.
They work much better than the other two.
self-attention은 다른 두 방법보다 훨씬 더 잘 작동합니다.
They are more expensive.
비용은 더 큽니다.
They do add computation and memory requirements,
computation과 memory 요구량이 더 늘어나지만,
but that comes with much better modeling of the sequence
그 대신 sequence를 훨씬 더 잘 모델링하고,
and better results in terms of any of the tasks.
어떤 task에서든 더 좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
So until here, it was mostly talking about self-attention.
여기까지는 대체로 self-attention에 관한 이야기였습니다.
We also talked a little bit about
그리고 우리는 또
cross-attention and related topics.
cross-attention과 관련된 주제들도 조금 다뤘습니다.
And then we got to the topic of vision transformers, which
그런 다음 우리는 vision transformer라는 주제로 넘어갔는데,
is one of the core models that is
이는 현대 Computer Vision application에서
being used in modern applications, Computer Vision
사용되는 핵심 model 중 하나입니다.
We did go through this in the last minutes of last lecture,
저번 강의, 즉 지난 lecture의 마지막 몇 분 동안
the previous lecture.
이 내용을 다뤘었죠.
And I want to revisit the topic.
그리고 저는 이 주제를 다시 살펴보고 싶습니다.
And after that, I'll stop and hear any questions or comments,
그 이후에는 잠시 멈추고 assignment나 지금까지 이야기한
you may have regarding the assignments and everything
모든 것에 관해 여러분이 가진 질문이나 의견을
that I talked about so far.
들어보겠습니다.
We talked about the fact that what
우리가 이야기했던 것은,
we do with transformers, when we want to process images,
transformer로 이미지를 처리하고 싶을 때 우리가 하는 일은
we split the image into patches, basically creating a sequence.
이미지를 patch들로 나누어서 기본적으로 sequence를 만드는 것입니다.
The image was split to S by S or in this case, maybe a 3
이미지는 S by S로 나뉘었는데, 이 경우에는 아마
by 3 patches.
3 by 3 patch였을 겁니다.
And each of those patches are then
그리고 그 각각의 patch들은
represented by what we call tokens.
우리가 token이라고 부르는 것으로 표현됩니다.
And tokens are often a linear projection
그리고 token은 보통
of the vector, the reshaped version
이미지를 벡터 형태로 reshape한 버전을
of the image into a vector.
linear projection한 것입니다.
And it's basically a D-dimensional vector,
그리고 슬라이드에서 보시는 것처럼 기본적으로 D-dimensional vector입니다.
But because we have turned the image
하지만 이미지를 patch로 바꿨기 때문에
into patches, what becomes important-- what
중요해지는 것이 있는데-- 우리가 여기서 잃는 것이 무엇일까요?
It's basically we're losing the position,
바로 이미지의 위치 정보, 즉 2D position을
the 2D position of the image.
잃어버린다는 것입니다.
So that's why we often create or add something that we
그래서 우리는 흔히 positional embedding이라고 부르는 것을
call positional embedding.
만들어서 추가합니다.
And there are many different ways of doing this.
그리고 이를 수행하는 방법에는 여러 가지가 있습니다.
You can create a sequence, just put numbers of sequence as 1,
sequence를 만들어서 그냥 1, 2, 3, ... 이런 식으로
2, 3, and so on.
번호를 매길 수도 있고,
Or you can do a 2D version of x and y-coordinates,
x, y 좌표를 사용하는 2D 버전으로 할 수도 있습니다.
and adding these two together creates the new token that goes
그리고 이 둘을 더하면 새로운 token이 만들어지고, 이것이
to the transformer layer the same way all
지난주 우리가 이야기했던 self-attention, layer norm,
of the self-attention, layer norm,
MLP 등 모든 것을 포함한
and everything that we've talked about, MLP, everything,
transformer layer로 동일하게 들어갑니다.
And then the output layer will generate the output vectors
그리고 output layer는 우리를 위해 output vector들을
for us.
생성합니다.
It could be used for any application.
이것은 어떤 application에도 사용될 수 있습니다.
One of the major applications in Computer Vision
Computer Vision에서 가장 주요한 application
has been classification.
중 하나는 classification이었습니다.
We started with image classification.
우리는 image classification부터 시작했었죠.
So with image classification, what becomes important
image classification에서 중요한 것은
is to somehow be able to encode or generate something
어떻게든 class를 대표하는 어떤 것을 encoding하거나
as the output that is representative of the class.
output으로 생성할 수 있어야 한다는 것입니다.
So what we do is often, we add one token, a special extra input
그래서 우리가 흔히 하는 것은 transformer에 하나의 token,
to the transformer, which is of the same dimensionality,
즉 같은 차원을 가지지만
but it's a learnable parameter that
학습 가능한 parameter인 특별한 추가 input을
in the output space, whatever that represents
넣는 것인데, 이것이 output space에서 나타내는 것이
is going to be turned into the class probability vector.
결국 class probability vector로 변환됩니다.
So a C-dimensional vector, which is the class probabilities.
즉, class probability인 C-dimensional vector입니다.
And that's what we often call the class token.
그리고 우리는 이것을 흔히 class token이라고 부릅니다.
So this is one of the base and most standard way
이것이 image classification을 위해 ViT, 즉 vision transformer를
of doing using ViTs, vision transformers,
사용하는 가장 기본적이고 표준적인 방법 중 하나입니다.
But transformers are not only used for classification,
하지만 transformer는 classification에만 쓰이는 것이 아니라
they could be used for many other tasks
다른 많은 task에도 사용될 수 있습니다.
that we will be covering some of those today as well.
그 중 일부를 오늘 다룰 예정입니다.
But last week, we also talked about this other variant
하지만 지난주에 우리는 transformer의 다른 변형에
of the transformers.
대해서도 이야기했습니다.
Again, same tokens.
동일한 token들을 사용하고,
And from the tokens we go with the transformer layers.
그 token들로부터 transformer layer로 넘어갑니다.
If you remember last time, we talked
지난 시간을 기억하신다면,
about these multiple layers of transformers.
우리는 이 여러 개의 transformer layer들에 대해
As I said, positional embeddings are added.
이야기했습니다. 말씀드렸듯이, positional embedding이 추가됩니다.
And here, because we see the entire image all together,
그리고 여기서는 이미지 전체를 한 번에 보기 때문에
we don't have to do masking like we
언어에서 했던 것처럼 masking을 할 필요가 없습니다.
did for language, because language is really a sequence
왜냐하면 언어는 정말 sequence이고
that we shouldn't be using the future information for.
미래의 정보를 사용하면 안 되기 때문입니다.
And then, ultimately, transformers
그리고 결국
give an output of a vector patch for each of the inputs.
transformer는 각 input에 대해 patch vector 형태의 output을 출력합니다.
And the other option for training a transformer
그리고 transformer를 학습시키는 또 다른 옵션은
is actually to instead of having a separate class token,
별도의 class token을 두는 대신 output들을 전부 가져와서
just take the outputs, run a pooling layer,
pooling layer를 적용한 다음,
and then turn that into a probability
그것을 C개의 서로 다른 class에 대한
vector for C different classes.
probability vector로 바꾸는 것입니다.
So I talked about two versions of transformers.
그래서 저는 transformer의 두 가지 버전에 대해 이야기했습니다.
One of them was we're using a class token.
하나는 class token을 사용하는 것이고,
And the other one was we take all of the output tokens.
다른 하나는 모든 output token을 전부 가져와서
We apply pooling and projection into a vector that represents
pooling과 projection을 적용해 class probability를
the class probabilities.
나타내는 vector로 만드는 것입니다.
How we supervise this?
이것을 어떻게 supervise할까요?
It's the exact same thing that we talked about earlier.
이전에 이야기했던 것과 정확히 동일합니다.
And that was back propagation, defining
바로 back propagation이었고, loss function을 정의하는 것이었죠.
a loss function, binary cross-entropy, the soft log, max
binary cross-entropy, softmax loss 등이 있었습니다.
So this was ViTs.
자, 이것이 ViT였습니다.
This is ViTs in a nutshell.
요약하면 이것이 ViT입니다.
And over the years, this type of architecture
그리고 세월이 지나면서, 이런 종류의 architecture는
for many different applications have remained the same.
여러 application에서 동일하게 유지되어 왔습니다.
Many modern architectures right now use many of these components
많은 현대 architecture들이 지금 여기서 소개한 것과
very similar to what we presented here.
매우 유사한 구성요소들을 많이 사용하고 있습니다.
But there are some optimizations that we
하지만 지난주 슬라이드에 있었던 몇 가지 최적화 기법들이
had in the slides last week, but I
있는데,
think I'll just spend quickly a couple of minutes on them.
그것들에 대해 잠깐 몇 분만 할애하려고 합니다.
But I want you to understand that there
하지만 여러분이 이해하셨으면 하는 것은,
are many different tweaks and optimizations for better
더 나은 성능을 위한, 그리고 transformer의 학습을 조금 더
performance, and also making the transformers, the training
안정적으로 만들기 위한 다양한 tweak과 최적화 기법들이
a little bit more stable.
많이 존재한다는 것입니다.
One of them is actually the residual connections.
그 중 하나가 바로 residual connection입니다.
This layer norm is basically outside the residual
이 layer norm은 기본적으로 residual 바깥에 있습니다.
So this means that whatever we get here, we normalize it.
즉, 여기서 얻은 것을 normalize한다는 뜻입니다.
So this doesn't really mean that we can't replicate
그래서 이것은 우리가 원했던 identity function을 더 이상
any form of identity function anymore, that resonates really
어떤 형태로도 재현할 수 없다는 것을 의미하지는 않습니다.
So the solution for that is to bring
그래서 그에 대한 해결책은
in the layer normalization.
layer normalization을 도입하는 것입니다.
We often put it before self-attention
우리는 흔히 self-attention 앞에 하나를 두고,
and the second one before the MLP layer.
MLP layer 앞에 두 번째 것을 둡니다.
So normalization is there.
그렇게 normalization이 존재합니다.
But we also preserve our identity function.
하지만 identity function도 동시에 보존됩니다.
There are also other ways of normalizing.
normalization을 하는 다른 방법들도 있습니다.
There is this RMSNorm, root mean square normalization,
RMSNorm, 즉 root mean square normalization이라는 것이 있는데,
which is actually a very basic type of normalization.
이것은 사실 매우 기본적인 형태의 normalization입니다.
For each of the features, it doesn't
각 feature에 대해
use the mean value of the feature for normalization.
normalization을 할 때 feature의 mean 값을 사용하지 않습니다.
But this makes the training a little bit more stable.
하지만 이것이 학습을 조금 더 안정적으로 만들어줍니다.
Again, these are all empirically shown to be better options.
다시 말씀드리지만, 이런 것들은 전부 경험적으로 더 나은 옵션임이
Although there are some justifications
입증된 것들입니다. 비록 왜 잘 작동하는지에
why while they work well.
대한 근거가 일부 있긴 하지만요.
But mostly, the reason for adopting these
하지만 대부분의 경우 이런 것들을 채택하는 이유는
is just the fact that they make the trainings more stable.
단순히 학습을 더 안정적으로 만들어주기 때문입니다.
The other option is to instead of using a simple MLP,
다른 옵션은 단순한 MLP 대신에
we use a SwiGLU MLP, where we actually do some--
SwiGLU MLP를 사용하는 것인데, 여기서 우리는--
this is what we call gated nonlinearity.
이것을 gated nonlinearity라고 부릅니다.
Instead of having two vectors of weights, matrices of W1 and W2,
weight matrix W1, W2 두 개를 갖는 대신,
we add a third one, 1, 2, and 3.
세 번째 것을 추가해서 1, 2, 3이 됩니다.
But here, we create some gated nonlinearity.
여기서 우리는 어떤 gated nonlinearity를 만들어냅니다.
Basically, what it does is getting more trainable
기본적으로 이것이 하는 일은 더 많은 trainable parameter를
parameters and not just necessarily
얻는 것뿐 아니라,
trainable parameters, but creating a better nonlinearity
작은 architecture에 대해 더 나은 nonlinearity를
for a small architecture.
만들어내는 것입니다.
Even if we select the hidden layer value equal to 8
hidden layer의 값을 8/3로 선택하더라도
divided by 3, it keeps the same size
network의 parameter 개수 측면에서는 동일한 크기를
of the network in terms of the number of parameters,
유지하지만,
but it does learn higher dimensional nonlinearities
그 layer에서 더 높은 차원의 nonlinearity를 학습하게 됩니다.
The last piece is mixture of experts
마지막으로 다룰 것은 mixture of experts인데,
that is often used in even the very modern architectures
이것은 요즘 매우 현대적인 architecture에서도
these days.
자주 사용됩니다.
Instead of having one set of MLP layers,
하나의 MLP layer 세트를 갖는 대신,
we can have multiple sets of MLP layers.
여러 세트의 MLP layer를 가질 수 있습니다.
Each of those will be an expert.
그 각각이 하나의 expert가 됩니다.
And what we do is through a router,
그리고 우리가 하는 것은 router를 통해서
the tokens will be routed to A of those E experts.
token들이 E개의 expert 중 A개로 라우팅됩니다.
And in this way, we actually have A active experts.
이런 식으로 우리는 실제로 A개의 active expert를 갖게 됩니다.
But then, again, what it does is it
그리고 이것이 하는 일은
increases the number of parameters,
parameter 개수를 늘리는 것이고,
and it helps learning more robust models without increasing
compute를 너무 많이 늘리지 않으면서 더 견고한 model을
too much on the compute.
학습하는 데 도움을 줍니다.
And these, again, are all parallel MLPs.
그리고 이것들은 모두 병렬적인 MLP들입니다.
So we can have multiple experts in parallel.
그래서 여러 expert를 병렬로 가질 수 있습니다.
As I said, they are used in all LLMs
말씀드렸듯이, 오늘날 모든 LLM, large language model에서
these days, large language models,
이것이 사용되고 있고,
and all of the modern LLMs up to the level
우리가 아는 수준까지의 모든 현대 LLM들이
that we know about are using these types of tweaks.
이런 종류의 tweak들을 사용하고 있습니다.
And this is the summary of all of the tweaks
그리고 이것이 제가 방금 언급한 tweak들의
that I just mentioned.
요약입니다.
This is similar to [? bias. ?] No.
이것이 bias와 비슷한 건가요? 아닙니다.
This is completely a trainable parameter by itself
이것은 완전히 별도로 학습하는 trainable parameter이고,
that you train, either a feedforward network or just
feedforward network든 아니면 단순한 linear projection이든
a linear projection to turn that into the probability vector.
그것을 probability vector로 바꾸도록 학습됩니다.
So it's not [? just bias. ?]
그러니까 그냥 bias는 아닙니다.
And then again, remember that you
그리고 다시 말씀드리지만,
have so many self-attention networks here, layers here.
여기 이 self-attention network, layer들이 아주 많이 있죠.
And those self-attention layers are
그리고 그 self-attention layer들은
basically fusing the information,
기본적으로 정보를 융합하는데,
creating attention between all of the tokens and this class
모든 token들과 이 class token 사이에 attention을
token.
만들어냅니다.
So when you supervise it from here,
그래서 여기서 supervise를 하면,
the loss function comes in.
loss function이 들어옵니다.
This will represent the class probabilities vector.
이것이 class probability vector를 나타낼 것입니다.
So the question is, if there are nice intuitions,
질문은, 각 expert가 무엇을 하는지에 대한
what different experts are doing?
좋은 직관이 있는지에 관한 것이군요.
That's a great question.
좋은 질문입니다.
Because they are trained in parallel,
왜냐하면 이들은 병렬로 학습되고,
and they are initialized differently,
서로 다르게 초기화되기 때문에,
they often try to learn one aspect or a related, maybe also
각각이 한 측면 혹은 관련된, 때로는 매우 밀접하게 관련된
sometimes very much related aspect,
측면을 학습하려는 경향이 있습니다.
but it's just adding more compute and more parameters,
하지만 그냥 더 많은 compute와 더 많은 parameter를 추가해서,
giving the network to learn different things, if it
network가 여러 개념을 학습해야 할 경우
does have to learn multiple concepts.
서로 다른 것들을 학습할 수 있는 능력을 주는 것입니다.
For example, if you have to cover multiple probability
예를 들어, 여러 probability distribution을
distributions, then with these MLPs,
다뤄야 한다면, 이런 MLP들을 통해
you often have the power to separate those modes of data.
데이터의 여러 mode를 분리할 수 있는 힘을 자주 얻게 됩니다.
So the question is, if the number of experts
질문은, expert 개수가
is a hyperparameter or not?
hyperparameter인지 아닌지에 관한 것이군요.
Yes, definitely, it's a hyperparameter.
네, 확실히 hyperparameter입니다.
From what I know, it's often predefined.
제가 아는 한, 보통은 미리 정해집니다.
Don't necessarily like over fine tune them.
굳이 그것을 과도하게 fine-tune하지는 않습니다.
But yes, they are all hyperparameters.
하지만 네, 이것들은 모두 hyperparameter입니다.
They are also learned.
학습되기도 합니다.
Yes.
네.
And they are learned.
그리고 학습됩니다.
So why moving the layer norm helps us
그럼 layer norm을 옮기는 것이 왜 identity transformation을
learn identity transformation?
학습하는 데 도움이 될까요?
So look at this architecture.
이 architecture를 보세요.
Will you be able to create any form of identity?
어떤 형태로든 identity를 만들 수 있을까요?
Because right after that residual connection,
왜냐하면 그 residual connection 바로 뒤에서
the feature values are changed, because you
feature 값들이 바뀌기 때문입니다,
have a normalization.
normalization이 있으니까요.
You will never have the identity in the features.
feature에서는 절대 identity를 가질 수 없습니다.
Because right after that, you see the layer normalization.
왜냐하면 바로 그 뒤에 layer normalization이 있으니까요.
And that's why, what we do is we bring it in.
그래서 우리가 하는 것은 그것을 안쪽으로 가져오는 것입니다.
We have quite a few different tasks in Computer Vision.
Computer Vision에는 꽤 다양한 task들이 있습니다.
And these were the core and the most important tasks
그리고 이것들이 지난 수년간 Computer Vision application에서
over the years for Computer Vision applications.
가장 핵심적이고 중요한 task들이었습니다.
Although these days, we are solving much harder tasks.
비록 요즘은 훨씬 더 어려운 task들을 풀고 있지만요.
And nobody cares about object detection anymore,
그리고 이제는 아무도 object detection에 신경 쓰지 않습니다,
because now, we can just do it with one line of code.
왜냐하면 이제는 코드 한 줄로 할 수 있으니까요.
But over the past 10, 15 years, there
하지만 지난 10, 15년 동안
has been a lot of advances.
많은 발전이 있었습니다.
And we want to cover, I want to really cover some of those
그래서 저는 오늘 그 중 일부를 정말로
today.
다루고 싶습니다.
Just so if you have to design something new yourself,
여러분이 직접 새로운 것을 설계해야 할 때,
you know where to look and how to design your models.
어디를 봐야 하고 model을 어떻게 설계해야 하는지 알 수 있도록요.
And then, ultimately, there is the topic
그리고 결국, visualization과
of visualization and understanding, which is very
understanding이라는 주제가 있는데, 이것은 많은 application에서
important in many applications.
매우 중요합니다.
For example, if you're working with medical data,
예를 들어, medical data를 다룬다면,
often, the visualization understanding
흔히 visualization과 understanding이
is more important than the classification itself
classification 자체나 tumor detection보다
or detection of tumor, for example,
더 중요합니다, 만약 어디에서, 왜 그런지를
if you want to know where, why, and so on.
알고 싶다면 말이죠.
The way we started the class, and this slide is probably
우리가 이 수업을 시작했던 방식대로,
very much familiar to everybody, we talked about different tasks.
아마 모두에게 매우 익숙할 이 슬라이드로, 여러 task를 이야기했었죠.
And for object classification, for the task of classification,
object classification, 즉 classification이라는 task에 대해서는
we talked about this.
이미 이야기했습니다.
We spent quite a lot of time over the first few lectures,
초반 몇 lecture에 걸쳐 꽤 많은 시간을 들여서
seeing how we can create a classifier that classifies
pixel에서 label로 이미지를 분류하는 classifier를
images from pixels into labels.
어떻게 만들 수 있는지 살펴봤습니다.
But then one of the other tasks important similarly
하지만 그것만큼 중요한 다른 task 중 하나가
is semantic segmentation.
semantic segmentation입니다.
And within semantic segmentation,
semantic segmentation에서
what we care about is to assign a label to every single pixel
우리가 신경 쓰는 것은 이미지 안의 모든 pixel에
inside the image, turn each of the pixels
label을 부여하는 것, 즉 각 pixel을
into a label that is the label for that object
그 장면에 있는 object나 무언가에 대한 label로
or anything in the scene.
바꾸는 것입니다.
So basically, when we train a model that
그래서 기본적으로, 이 작업을 하는 model을 학습시킬 때,
does this at the test time, we want to take an image
test time에 이미지를 받아서
and generate the same map as the output.
그것과 동일한 map을 output으로 생성하고 싶습니다.
How do we do that?
어떻게 그렇게 할까요?
There are many different options.
여러 가지 옵션이 있습니다.
So let's say, what I can do is just
예를 들어, 제가 할 수 있는 것은 그냥
look at each pixel, every single pixel, and say what the value
각 pixel, 모든 개별 pixel을 보고 그 pixel의 값이나
or what the label for that pixel should be.
label이 무엇이어야 하는지 말하는 것입니다.
In the very basic form, as you can see here,
아주 기본적인 형태로는, 여기 보시는 것처럼,
it's actually very much impossible.
사실상 거의 불가능합니다.
It's hard to say what pixel that represents that specific-- what
pixel 자체만 본다면, 그 특정 pixel이 어떤 object를 나타내는지
object that specific pixel represents because there
말하기가 어렵습니다, 왜냐하면
is no context, if you only look at the pixel itself.
context가 없기 때문입니다.
So that's why context is important.
그래서 context가 중요합니다.
We look at the surrounding areas.
우리는 주변 영역을 봅니다.
And then if I take these patches and the pixel
그리고 이 patch들과 가운데 pixel,
in the center and the surrounding areas,
그리고 주변 영역을 가져다가,
now, I can train a convolutional neural network
convolutional neural network나 output label을 생성해줄
or any network that generates the output label for us.
어떤 network든 학습시킬 수 있습니다.
It's the same architecture that we've
이번 quarter 내내 이야기했던 것과
talked about over the quarter.
동일한 architecture입니다.
And you can select any of those that we
그리고 image classification에 사용했던 것 중
used for image classification.
아무거나 선택할 수 있습니다.
Because now, you're classifying the entire image.
왜냐하면 이제 전체 이미지를 classification하는 것이니까요.
It could be a CNN, it could be a ResNet, it could be a ViT,
CNN이든, ResNet이든, ViT든 뭐든 될 수 있습니다.
This is really time consuming because if you
이것은 사실 매우 시간이 많이 걸리는데, 왜냐하면
want to run one full network for every single pixel in an image,
이미지의 모든 개별 pixel에 대해 전체 network를 한 번씩
it will take forever to turn this into a segmentation map.
돌려야 한다면 segmentation map을 만드는 데 아주 오래 걸리기 때문입니다.
The other option that we can use is
우리가 쓸 수 있는 다른 옵션은
to instead of running one network for every single pixel,
모든 개별 pixel에 대해 network를 하나씩 돌리는 대신,
what if we train a neural network that
이미지를 input으로 받아서
takes the image as the input and outputs the entire pixel map,
전체 pixel map, 즉 segmentation map을 output으로
the segmentation map, not just one single label,
출력하는 neural network를 학습시키는 것입니다,
a matrix of labels?
단일 label 하나가 아니라 label들의 matrix를요.
And in that case, we will have our segmentation task solved.
그렇게 하면 우리의 segmentation task가 해결됩니다.
And in order to do that, we need to have
그리고 그렇게 하기 위해서는,
a layer in the input that is the same size as the image.
input layer가 이미지와 동일한 크기를 가져야 합니다.
And also in the output, we also need
그리고 output도
some sort of an inflated layer.
어느 정도 부풀려진(inflated) layer가 필요합니다.
You can't go to fully connected layers, and so on, because now,
fully connected layer 등으로 갈 수는 없습니다, 왜냐하면 이제
we are generating an image.
우리는 이미지를 생성하고 있으니까요.
And because of that, we need to keep the network inflated.
그래서 network를 계속 inflated 상태로 유지해야 합니다.
And then that's what we call, often, fully convolutional
그리고 이것을 흔히 fully convolutional
neural networks or FCNs.
neural network, FCN이라고 부릅니다.
So with fully convolutional neural networks,
fully convolutional neural network는
this is definitely a great idea.
확실히 좋은 아이디어입니다.
But there is a caveat.
하지만 한 가지 문제가 있습니다.
There is a problem.
문제가 하나 있죠.
These images are large.
이미지들은 크다는 것입니다.
And these networks, these layers will become very large.
그리고 이런 network들, layer들이 매우 커지게 됩니다.
And there will be so many parameters
최적화해야 할 parameter가 너무 많아지는데,
to optimize, especially in the early years
특히 강력한 GPU가 없던 초창기에는
that we didn't have powerful GPUs,
이것이 학습 알고리즘에 있어
this was a bottleneck, a problem, a challenge
병목이자 문제, challenge였습니다.
And that's why the algorithms evolved
그래서 알고리즘은 전체 크기의 이미지에서
into starting from full-size images going down
시작해서 resolution을 점점 낮춰가는 방향으로
in terms of the resolution, making
발전했습니다. downsampling 연산을 통해
the convolutions, the spatial resolutions smaller and smaller
convolution, spatial resolution을 점점 작게 만들면서요.
And then somewhere in the middle,
그리고 중간 어딘가에서는,
we will have a low resolution, but somehow thick
resolution은 낮지만 channel 수 측면에서는
in terms of the number of channels.
어느 정도 두꺼운 상태를 갖게 됩니다.
And then from there, what we do is
그리고 거기서부터
we go back up to the same size of the image
다시 원래 이미지 크기로 되돌아가서
to create the output pixel.
output pixel을 만듭니다.
And in order to do that, we know how to do the downsampling.
그리고 그렇게 하려면, 우리는 downsampling하는
Downsampling was easy.
방법을 알아야 합니다. downsampling은 쉬웠죠.
We've talked about it.
이미 이야기했었습니다.
We talked about pooling operation, strided convolution,
pooling 연산, strided convolution,
and several other steps or operations that
그리고 여기서 쓸 수 있는 몇 가지 다른 단계나
could be used here.
연산들도 이야기했습니다.
But on the upsampling side, we don't really
하지만 upsampling 쪽에서는, 사실 우리가
know how to do the upsampling because we don't have pooling
upsampling을 어떻게 해야 할지 잘 모릅니다, 왜냐하면
or reverse of up pooling or reverse strided convolutions.
pooling이나 up pooling, 혹은 strided convolution의 역연산이 없기 때문입니다.
And because of that, we had to invent
그래서 우리는
some new operations that reverses downsampling by itself.
downsampling을 스스로 역전시키는 새로운 연산을 발명해야 했습니다.
But before I go to the upsampling,
하지만 upsampling으로 가기 전에,
defining what upsampling is, I just briefly
upsampling이 무엇인지 정의하기에 앞서, 잠깐
want to tell you that, maybe I can ask you a question.
질문 하나를 드리고 싶습니다.
How do you think this network is trained?
이 network가 어떻게 학습된다고 생각하시나요?
Because now, we have a network that starts from an image
왜냐하면 이제 우리는 이미지에서 시작해서 이미지로
and ends with an image.
끝나는 network를 가지고 있으니까요.
And then the tools that we have for training this network
그리고 이 network를 학습시키기 위한 도구는
was a loss function.
loss function이었습니다.
How do you think is the best to train or define a loss
이 network를 위한 loss function을 정의하거나
function for this network?
학습시키는 가장 좋은 방법이 뭐라고 생각하시나요?
We talked about softmax loss.
우리는 softmax loss에 대해 이야기했었죠.
We talked also a little bit about some regression losses
그리고 regression loss와
and SVM loss.
SVM loss에 대해서도 조금 이야기했습니다.
But assuming that we want to use softmax loss function,
하지만 softmax loss function을 쓴다고 가정하면,
how could we define this or train this network?
이 network를 어떻게 정의하거나 학습시킬 수 있을까요?
What would the objective be?
목적함수(objective)는 무엇이어야 할까요?
So you said mean classification loss for each of the pixels.
각 pixel에 대한 mean classification loss라고 하셨군요.
And that's correct.
맞습니다.
You can add the loss function for every single pixel,
모든 개별 pixel에 대해 loss function을 더할 수 있습니다,
because every single pixel is doing a classification.
왜냐하면 모든 개별 pixel이 classification을 하고 있으니까요.
So you will have a sigma over all pixels of the image.
그래서 이미지의 모든 pixel에 대한 sigma 합을 갖게 됩니다.
And the loss function is just a simple softmax.
그리고 loss function은 그냥 단순한 softmax입니다.
And then you can backprop.
그런 다음 backprop을 할 수 있습니다.
That's the entire loss function that you need.
필요한 loss function은 그게 전부입니다.
The question is, do we need, what we call,
질문은, 우리가 흔히 말하는 ground truth가
ground truths for training?
학습에 필요한지에 관한 것이군요.
So that's actually the ground truths of segmentation.
네, 그건 실제로 segmentation의 ground truth입니다.
And yes, for these types of algorithms,
그리고 이런 종류의 알고리즘은
because they are fully supervised,
fully supervised이기 때문에,
we do need the ground truths label maps.
우리는 ground truth label map이 필요합니다.
And early years, there has been a lot
초창기에는
of work doing and sitting down and manually labeling
이런 알고리즘을 학습시키기 위해 앉아서 수동으로
the pixels to be able to train these algorithms.
pixel을 label링하는 작업이 정말 많았습니다.
Yes.
네.
These days, we don't need that because we have tools.
요즘은 도구들이 있어서 그럴 필요가 없습니다.
But early on, in order to train these algorithms,
하지만 초창기에는 이런 알고리즘을 학습시키려면
we needed the ground truth.
ground truth가 필요했습니다.
Very briefly, let me tell you what we do with upsampling.
아주 간단히, upsampling에서 우리가 하는 일을 말씀드리겠습니다.
Upsampling is actually not that hard.
upsampling은 사실 그렇게 어렵지 않습니다.
We can use an unpooling operation.
unpooling 연산을 사용할 수 있습니다.
There are different ways of doing it.
이를 수행하는 방법에는 여러 가지가 있습니다.
One is nearest neighbor.
하나는 nearest neighbor입니다.
If I want to go from a 2 by 2 as an example here,
예를 들어 2 by 2 matrix를 4 by 4로 만들고 싶다면,
I just need to copy the data for each of these,
낮은 resolution의 값에서 가장 가까운 이웃(nearest neighbor)을
take the nearest neighbor in the lower resolution one.
가져와 각각에 데이터를 복사하기만 하면 됩니다.
Or bed of nails is you just select
또는 bed of nails 방식은 upsampled 버전에서
one of those in the upsampled version.
그 중 하나만 선택하는 것입니다.
You only select one of those, the one in the corner.
모서리에 있는 것 하나만 선택해서
To copy the data, replace everything else with zero.
데이터를 복사하고, 나머지는 전부 0으로 채웁니다.
And through multiple layers of convolution,
그리고 여러 layer의 convolution을 거치면서,
these values will start appearing.
이 값들이 나타나기 시작합니다.
If we use max pooling in our network,
만약 network의 encoding 쪽에서 max pooling을
in the encoding side, what we can do
사용한다면, 우리가 할 수 있는 것은
is we can save the locations of the max, the ones that
선택되었던 max값의 위치를 저장해두고,
were selected, and then copy the data in the unpooling max,
decoding 쪽의 unpooling stage에서 max가 정의되었던
unpooling stage right over there that the max was defined.
바로 그 위치에 데이터를 복사하는 것입니다.
So basically, we save the locations.
즉, 기본적으로 위치를 저장하는 것입니다.
In the encoding part and in decoding part
encoding 부분에서 저장한 좌표를
in the upsampling step, we reuse those saved coordinates.
decoding 부분의 upsampling 단계에서 재사용합니다.
The other option is to do a learned upsampling.
다른 옵션은 learned upsampling을 하는 것입니다.
All of these that I showed there is no parameter to be learned.
지금까지 보여드린 것들은 학습할 parameter가 없습니다.
It's just an operation.
그냥 하나의 연산일 뿐입니다.
But learned upsampling are also possible.
하지만 learned upsampling도 가능합니다.
Very simply, let's revisit the convolution.
아주 간단하게, convolution을
In the convolution layer, what we did
다시 살펴보겠습니다. convolution layer에서
was applying a convolution filter for a pixel
우리가 한 것은 하나의 pixel에 convolution filter를
and generating the output, and do this repeatedly
적용해서 output을 생성하고, 이를 모든 pixel에 대해
for all of the pixels.
반복적으로 수행하는 것이었습니다.
And when we wanted to do--
그리고 downsample을 하고 싶을 때--
to downsample, what we did was strided
우리가 한 것은 strided convolution이었죠, 1 step씩
convolution, where, instead of taking steps of 1,
가는 대신 2 step씩 가면서
we take steps of 2, and generate the outputs step by step.
output을 단계적으로 생성하는 것이었습니다.
If you don't remember this part, go back to the lecture.
이 부분이 기억나지 않으신다면 강의를 다시 확인해보세요.
We talked about it.
이미 이야기했었습니다.
Third lecture, I think.
아마 세 번째 강의였을 겁니다.
And then we can replicate the same for the upsampling process.
그리고 upsampling 과정에도 같은 것을 그대로 적용할 수 있습니다.
So this one will represent this area in the upsampled image.
그러면 이것이 upsampled 이미지의 이 영역을 나타내게 됩니다.
And then we define some weights here
그리고 output map에
to map that to the output map.
이를 매핑하기 위해 여기에 weight를 정의합니다.
And then for the next one, same story,
그리고 다음 것도 동일한 방식이지만,
but there will be overlaps.
겹치는 부분이 생깁니다.
And for the overlaps, we often sum over the values.
그리고 겹치는 부분에 대해서는 흔히 값들을 합칩니다.
Let me give you an example, sum over the outputs.
예를 들어 output에 대해 합산하는 것을 보여드리겠습니다.
Let me give you an example.
예를 들어 보겠습니다.
And that's with a simple 1D function.
간단한 1D 함수로 설명드리겠습니다.
If the input is just two values of A and B,
input이 그냥 A와 B라는 두 값이라면,
we learn a filter that that filter maps it to the higher
우리는 그것을 더 높은 resolution의 output으로 매핑하는
resolution output.
filter를 학습합니다.
And for doing that, we just apply the filter
그리고 그렇게 하기 위해서는 그냥 각 값에 filter를
to each of the values and write the outputs here.
적용하고 여기에 output을 쓰면 됩니다.
For the parts that there is an overlap, it's the summation.
겹치는 부분에 대해서는 합산(summation)을 합니다.
Addition of what is coming from each of the two locations.
각 두 위치에서 오는 값들을 더하는 것입니다.
So we did talk about this fully convolutional neural networks
자, 이렇게 fully convolutional neural network와
and how they are being used.
그것이 어떻게 사용되는지 이야기했습니다.
These are actually some of the most basic and mostly widely
이것들은 사실 segmentation에서 가장 기본적이고 가장
used algorithms for segmentation.
널리 사용되는 알고리즘 중 일부입니다.
And I want to also, very quickly,
그리고 저는 아주 빠르게
highlight one of the widely used networks units.
널리 사용되는 network 중 하나인 unit(U-Net)을 강조하고
As you can see, the shape U, it's
싶습니다. 보시는 것처럼,
actually the same architecture as I showed here.
모양이 U자 형태인데, 사실 여기서 보여드린 것과
Just let's draw it as similar to a U shape.
동일한 architecture입니다. 그냥 U자 모양으로 비슷하게
And the reason that I'm highlighting this
그려본 것뿐입니다.
is that still, today, some of the medical applications
그리고 제가 이것을 강조하는 이유는 지금도
that work on segmentation, use segmentation algorithms,
segmentation 알고리즘을 사용하는 일부 medical application에서는
still, this unit or its variants generate the state-of-the art
여전히 이 unit이나 그 변형들이
results, if you don't want to use any foundation model.
foundation model을 쓰고 싶지 않다면 state-of-the-art
So what it does is exactly what we explained.
결과를 만들어내기 때문입니다.
A downsampling phase that increases the field of view
이것이 하는 일은 정확히 우리가 설명한 것과 같습니다.
and loses some spatial information,
field of view를 늘리면서 일부 spatial 정보를 잃는
and then upsampling phase that goes back
downsampling 단계와, 다시 이미지 resolution으로
to the image resolution.
돌아가는 upsampling 단계가 있습니다.
The only difference that U-Net has
U-Net이 갖는 유일한 차이점은
is because it's used for segmentation,
이것이 segmentation에 사용되기 때문에,
there is this understanding that we
decoder 쪽에서 spatial 정보를 유지해야 한다는
need to keep the spatial information in the decoder side,
이해가 있다는 것입니다,
because when we downsample, we somehow lose resolution.
왜냐하면 downsample을 하면 어느 정도 resolution을 잃기 때문입니다.
And then upsampling, if you don't have the information,
그리고 그 정보가 없으면 upsampling할 때
it's going to be a little bit hard.
조금 어려워지게 됩니다.
And we often get into sometimes boundaries are faded.
그리고 종종 경계선(boundary)이 흐릿해지는 문제가 생깁니다.
And in order not to get the feature maps in the encoder side
그래서 이를 방지하기 위해, encoder 쪽의 feature map들이
are actually copied as inputs to the decoder layers.
실제로 decoder layer의 input으로 복사됩니다.
In that way, you're keeping this structural information
그렇게 함으로써 이미지 내의 구조적인 정보를 유지하면서
within the image and generate the outputs
훨씬 더 선명한 output을
that are much sharper.
생성할 수 있습니다.
So this was the idea behind U-Net And as I said,
이것이 U-Net 뒤에 있는 아이디어였고, 말씀드린 대로
it's actually being used quite often.
실제로 꽤 자주 사용되고 있습니다.
Summary of semantic segmentation--
semantic segmentation 요약--
what we talked about today, the fully convolutional
오늘 이야기한 것은 fully convolutional
neural networks.
neural network였습니다.
You have same filter as before that we
여기서 downsampling에 사용했던 것과
had for downsampling here.
동일한 filter를 갖습니다.
To save time, I actually removed some of the slides
시간을 아끼기 위해, 이 부분의 슬라이드는 일부 제거했습니다.
from this part.
슬라이드 뒷부분에 남겨두었으니
And I have it in the back of the slides.
꼭 확인해보시기 바랍니다.
This is a reverse.
이것은 역연산인,
This is transformed transposed convolution.
transposed convolution 입니다.
So we do have a 3 by 3 matrix here.
여기 3 by 3 matrix가 있습니다.
And then instead of convolving the input image, input data,
그리고 input 이미지, input data에 convolution을 적용하는 대신,
we do the convolution on the--
input의 transposed 버전에--
applied convolution on the transposed version of the input.
convolution을 적용합니다.
And it actually generates a larger output.
그러면 실제로 더 큰 output이 생성됩니다.
So it's the transposed convolution.
그래서 transposed convolution인 것입니다.
It's the reverse of the regular convolution.
일반 convolution의 역연산입니다.
But why transposed?
그런데 왜 transposed일까요?
I would refer you to take a look at the additional slides.
추가 슬라이드를 참고하시길 권해드립니다.
So the question is, is the filter trained?
질문은, filter가 학습되는지에 관한 것이군요.
Yes.
네.
It's very much similar to other convolution layers.
다른 convolution layer들과 매우 비슷합니다.
All of the filters are trained.
모든 filter는 학습됩니다.
Yes.
네.
Great.
좋습니다.
This was the topic of semantic segmentation.
이것이 semantic segmentation 이라는 주제였습니다.
And as we talked about this, we only get labels for the pixels.
그리고 지금까지 이야기했듯이, 우리는 pixel에 대한 label만 얻습니다.
But if there are two instances of the same object,
하지만 만약 동일한 object의 instance가 두 개 있다면,
we have no idea which one is which.
어느 것이 어느 것인지 전혀 알 수 없습니다.
Because this is just generating or outputting the pixel labels.
왜냐하면 이것은 그냥 pixel label만 출력하고 있기 때문입니다.
And that brings us to the topic of instance segmentation,
그리고 이것이 우리를 instance segmentation이라는
where now, we not only care about the pixel classes,
주제로 이끕니다. 여기서는 pixel class뿐만 아니라
but also, I want you to know that these pixels belong
이 pixel들이 개 한 마리의 instance에 속한다는 것도
to one instance of the dog.
알고 싶습니다.
And this next one is actually a different dog.
그리고 그 옆의 것은 사실 다른 개입니다.
And for doing that, what we need is understanding
그리고 그렇게 하기 위해 필요한 것은
multiple objects in the image and brings us
이미지 속의 여러 object를 이해하는 것이고, 이것이
to the topic of object detection.
object detection이라는 주제로 이어집니다.
Object detection has been one of the, besides image
object detection은 image classification 이후,
classification or after image classification,
혹은 그 옆에서
has been one of the core Computer Vision problems
core Computer Vision 문제이자 task 중 하나였습니다.
And for many years, many, many different algorithms
그리고 수년간, 정말 많은 서로 다른 알고리즘들이
were proposed for just doing the task of object detection.
오직 object detection이라는 task를 위해 제안되었습니다.
We are going to fly over some of them
우리는 그 중 일부를 훑어보면서
and highlight a couple of important ones.
몇 가지 중요한 것들을 강조할 것입니다.
But again, there are so many works in the literature,
하지만 다시 말씀드리지만, 문헌에는 매우 많은 연구가 있는데,
even in the literature of deep learning
deep learning 문헌에서도 지난 10, 15년 동안
that I am not covering here, so in the past 10, 15 years.
제가 여기서 다루지 못하는 것들이 많습니다.
How we can do that and solve the problem of object detection?
object detection 문제를 어떻게 풀 수 있을까요?
If it's just a single object, it means that we need to generate--
만약 object가 하나뿐이라면, 우리는--
we need to do the classification,
classification을 해야 하고,
generate a label class scores, as well
label class score를 생성해야 하며,
as getting a bounding box, coordinates of a box.
동시에 bounding box, 즉 box의 좌표도 얻어야 합니다.
So we need the coordinates of the box
그래서 우리는 box의 좌표
x, y, and h and w as the output, as well as what class it is.
x, y, h, w를 output으로 필요로 하고, 어떤 class인지도 필요합니다.
So this is exactly the task of object detection.
이것이 바로 object detection이라는 task입니다.
How can we solve this?
이것을 어떻게 풀 수 있을까요?
It's very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
We can define a softmax loss function for the class scores.
class score에 대해서는 softmax loss function을 정의할 수 있습니다.
And we can define an L2 loss function, which
그리고 box 좌표에 대해서는
is a simple distance metric, a regression loss for the box
간단한 거리 metric인 L2 loss function, 즉 regression loss를
coordinates.
정의할 수 있습니다.
And having these two defined, we have a multi-task loss.
이 두 가지를 정의하면, multi-task loss를 갖게 됩니다.
We are solving two tasks at the same time.
우리는 동시에 두 가지 task를 풀고 있는 것입니다.
And for doing that, we, again, add
그리고 그렇게 하기 위해 우리는 또
the loss values and generate a compound loss function,
loss 값들을 더해서 여기 보시는 것처럼 하나의
as you can see here.
compound loss function을 만듭니다.
So this is simple.
그래서 이것은 간단합니다.
It's doable.
할 수 있는 방법입니다.
If you have one single object, you can for sure
object가 하나뿐이라면, 제가 이야기한 이
solve this problem using this architecture
architecture로 이 문제를 확실히
that I talked about.
풀 수 있습니다.
But this is not that easy, if you have
하지만 장면에 object가
multiple objects in the scene.
여러 개 있으면 이렇게 쉽지 않습니다.
So for three objects, you have to generate 12 output numbers.
object가 3개라면, 12개의 output 숫자를 생성해야 합니다.
And if there are more, then it's going
그리고 더 많다면,
to be too many numbers to generate.
생성해야 할 숫자가 너무 많아지게 됩니다.
So this algorithm is not really scalable.
그래서 이 알고리즘은 사실 확장성이 없습니다(not scalable).
It's just extending the classification
그냥 classification을 object detection으로
into some object detection, which is fine,
확장한 것뿐이고, 괜찮긴 하지만,
but it's not really scalable.
확장성이 정말 없습니다.
So when there are multiple objects,
그래서 object가 여러 개 있을 때,
one solution is instead of going or getting the entire image
한 가지 해결책은 전체 이미지를 input으로 받는 대신,
as the input, why not to look at bounding boxes.
bounding box를 살펴보는 것입니다.
For each bounding box, we can say we only have one label,
각 bounding box에 대해, label을 하나만 가진다고 할 수 있습니다,
and whether it's a cat or a dog or the background.
고양이인지, 개인지, 아니면 background인지를요.
And if I have this way of classifying
그리고 이렇게 각 bounding box를 분류하는 방법이
each of the bounding boxes, I can do a sliding window.
있으면, sliding window를 할 수 있습니다.
I can create this bounding boxes,
이 bounding box를 만들고,
slide it over the image from coordinate 0, 0
좌표 0, 0부터
to all combination of x, y, and h and w,
x, y, h, w의 모든 조합까지 이미지 위로 슬라이딩시키면서
and see if we can detect the object.
object를 감지할 수 있는지 볼 수 있습니다.
So step by step, I can create--
그래서 단계별로--
I can find the bounding boxes that I
각 object에 대해 확률이
have the maximum probability of each of the objects.
최대인 bounding box를 찾을 수 있습니다.
But there is a huge problem here.
하지만 여기 큰 문제가 있습니다.
Again, there are so many different combinations
다시 말씀드리지만, 사용할 수 있는 bounding box의
of bounding boxes that you can use.
조합이 너무나 많습니다.
And again, this algorithm is not scalable.
그리고 이 알고리즘도 확장성이 없습니다.
What we've been doing in the literature, again,
그래서 문헌에서 해온 것을 보면, 다시 말씀드리지만,
early years, if you look at the years
초창기, 이 논문들이 발표된 연도를 보면
these articles were published, 2014,
2014년 및 그 이전인데,
and before, there has been a lot of research around finding
object가 있을 확률이 높은 영역을 찾는 것에 대한
regions that they have high probability
연구가 많이 있었습니다.
of having the object in them.
즉 region proposal입니다.
So region proposals.
그리고 region proposal을
And if I have a way to find region proposals,
찾는 방법이 있다면, 그것은 실제로 어느 정도
that's actually going to be an easy-ish problem.
쉬운 문제가 됩니다.
I can do the same thing as I explained earlier.
앞에서 설명한 것과 동일한 것을 할 수 있습니다.
For an image, what we can do is if I have region proposals,
이미지에 대해, region proposal이 있다면,
I can just take that part, that patch out
그 부분, 그 patch를 그대로 꺼내서
and run a CNN on that patch, a convolutional neural network
그 patch에 CNN, 즉 convolutional neural network를
on the patch, and then classify it.
돌려서 분류할 수 있습니다.
And in order to--
그리고--
even I can refine the bounding boxes.
심지어 bounding box를 정제(refine)할 수도 있습니다.
So classify and then refine the bounding boxes
그래서 classify한 다음 bounding box를 정제해서
to have the objects detected.
object를 검출하는 것입니다.
So we can classify the boxes and also refine
그래서 box를 분류할 수 있고, 좌표를 조금
the bounding boxes, if I have to change
바꿔야 한다면 bounding box도 정제할 수 있습니다.
And this is what is called R-CNN algorithm.
이것이 R-CNN이라고 불리는 알고리즘입니다.
And although it works, and, again, this is one of the early
그리고 비록 잘 작동하긴 하지만, 다시 말씀드리지만
algorithms up to 2014.
이것은 2014년까지의 초창기 알고리즘 중 하나입니다.
These are very slow because for each of these boxes, again,
이것들은 매우 느린데, 왜냐하면 각 box마다
we are running a full convolutional neural network.
다시 전체 convolutional neural network를 돌려야 하기 때문입니다.
But there is one catch that what we can do
하지만 한 가지 요령이 있는데, 우리가 할 수 있는 것은
is instead of running convolutional neural network
각 box마다 convolutional neural network를 돌리는 대신,
on each of these boxes, because convolution operations,
convolution 연산은 spatial 정보를 보존하기 때문에,
they preserve the spatial information.
downsample이든 upsample이든
They either downsample or upsample.
항상 그것들이 pixel 공간의 어디에 있는지
We always have a way to track them where in the pixel space
추적할 방법이 있습니다.
So in that case, what we do is instead of running
그래서 우리가 하는 것은, patch마다 convolutional
the convolutional neural network on the patches, let's say,
neural network를 돌리는 대신,
we run one big convolution on the entire image.
전체 이미지에 대해 큰 convolution 하나를 돌리는 것입니다.
And then now we have the regions in that feature
그러면 이제 전체 이미지에 대응하는 feature map에
map, which is corresponding to the entire image.
영역들이 생기게 됩니다.
Let's look at those regions.
그 영역들을 살펴봅시다.
And now, run a smaller CNN on top of those
그리고 이제 그 위에 더 작은 CNN을 돌려서
and generate the outputs for each of these two outputs
우리가 원하는 두 가지 output을 생성합니다,
First, the box offset.
먼저 box offset,
Should I move the bounding box a little bit?
bounding box를 조금 움직여야 하는지,
Or what's the object category is?
그리고 object category는 무엇인지입니다.
So this is the fast version of R-CNN
이것이 R-CNN의 fast 버전입니다.
These are some basic algorithms that we
이것들은 convolutional neural network를 사용해서
can use convolutional neural networks for detecting objects,
object와 bounding box 등을 검출할 수 있는 기본적인 알고리즘들입니다.
The question is, if the number of proposed regions
질문은, 제안되는(proposed) region의 개수가
are predefined?
미리 정해져 있는지에 관한 것이군요.
The short answer to that is yes.
간단히 답하면 네, 그렇습니다.
I will talk very briefly about the region proposal networks do.
region proposal network가 하는 일에 대해 아주 간단히
So easy algorithms.
간단한 알고리즘들입니다.
One, puts the bounding boxes of the regions, the proposed
하나는 제안된 region의 bounding box를
regions.
이미지 위에 두고,
Under the images, one puts it on the feature maps of the ConvNet.
다른 하나는 ConvNet의 feature map 위에 둡니다.
And both of those generate the output class label,
그리고 둘 다 output class label과
as well as offset of improving the location
검출된 object 위치를 개선하는 offset을
of the detected object.
생성합니다.
But this will mean, this requires
하지만 이것은,
us to do that bounding box region proposal first,
먼저 bounding box region proposal을 해야 한다는 것,
and have a region proposal network that tells us
그리고 이미지에서 어디를 봐야 하는지 알려주는
where in the image we should look for.
region proposal network가 필요하다는 것을 의미합니다.
And there has been research on building region proposal
그리고 region proposal network, RPN을
networks, RPNs.
만드는 연구가 있었습니다.
And here, what we do is we just randomly start with a CNN.
그리고 여기서 우리가 하는 것은, 그냥 CNN으로 무작위로 시작해서
We try to randomly start in different locations
이미지의 서로 다른 위치에서
in the image.
무작위로 시도합니다.
And through layers of convolution,
그리고 여러 layer의 convolution을 거치며,
we refine those regions where they have the higher probability
object label과 위치가 있으므로, object가 있을
of having an object in them, because we have the object
확률이 더 높은 영역으로 정제(refine)합니다.
labels and locations.
그래서 이것을 최적화하고, supervise할 수 있습니다.
And then each of those also refine the box coordinates.
그리고 각각은 box 좌표도 정제합니다.
So basically, a region proposal network, what it does
그래서 기본적으로, region proposal network가 하는 일은
is it refines the boxes, each of those boxes that
object가 있을 확률이 높은 box들을 정제해서
have a probability, a high probability of an object
output box로 만드는 것입니다.
The box corrections.
box correction입니다.
Again, I'm leaving all of the details about the coordinates
다시 말씀드리지만, 좌표나 차원에 대한 모든 세부사항은
and all of these dimensionalities
여러분이 나중에
for you to check afterwards, because they
직접 확인해보시도록 남겨두겠습니다, 왜냐하면
will take too much time.
시간이 너무 많이 걸리기 때문입니다.
And we don't want to spend too much time on this algorithm.
이 알고리즘에 너무 많은 시간을 쓰고 싶지 않습니다.
But what's important here is back to your question,
하지만 여기서 중요한 것은, 아까 질문으로 돌아가면,
we often take the top K, the ones
흔히 우리는 이 이미지에 대한 proposal로
that have the highest probability
object가 있을 확률이 가장 높은
of having an object in them as the proposals for this image.
상위 K개를 취합니다.
This is a simple image and only has one object.
이것은 단순한 이미지이고 object가 하나만 있습니다.
So most of the regions are centered
그래서 대부분의 region이
around that single object.
그 단일 object 주변에 집중되어 있습니다.
But, in general, that's not the case.
하지만 일반적으로는 그렇지 않습니다.
So in many setups, we can have region proposals
그래서 많은 설정에서 region proposal은
used in different setups.
다양한 방식으로 사용될 수 있습니다.
We can get different objects with higher probabilities.
더 높은 확률을 가진 서로 다른 object들을 얻을 수 있습니다.
With that, and after talking a little bit
자, R-CNN과 mask R-CNN에 대해 조금 이야기한 후,
about R-CNN and mask R-CNN, which, again, for you,
이는 여러분에게
it's important to go through the details.
세부사항을 직접 살펴보는 것이 중요합니다.
And if you can spend some time doing the calculations yourself,
직접 계산을 해보는 시간을 낼 수 있다면,
that would be very good.
정말 도움이 될 것입니다.
But those types of algorithms, R-CNN, mask R-CNN, they
하지만 이런 종류의 알고리즘, R-CNN, mask R-CNN은
are not being used anymore these days because they
요즘에는 더 이상 사용되지 않습니다, 왜냐하면
are very heavy computationally.
computation 부담이 매우 크기 때문입니다.
Although it's important to understand how
비록 우리가 어떻게 여기까지 왔는지 이해하는 것은
we got to this point.
중요하지만요.
But those are for many reasons.
그것들은 여러 이유가 있습니다.
One of those reasons is that we need two separate networks, one
그 중 하나는, 우리가 region proposal network 하나,
region proposal network, and then one classification and box
그리고 classification과 box refinement network 하나,
refinement network.
이렇게 두 개의 별도 network가 필요하다는 것입니다.
So it's like at least two passes for detecting objects
그래서 이미지마다 object를 검출하는 데
for each image.
최소 두 번의 pass가 필요합니다.
That's why there has been advances
그래서 single stage
after using single stage, object detectors, SSDs,
object detector, SSD를 사용하는 방향으로 발전이 있었고,
and one of the most popular ones is called YOLO.
가장 인기 있는 것 중 하나가 YOLO라고 불리는 것입니다.
YOLO is probably, if you work with any Computer Vision
YOLO는 아마 Computer Vision 문제를 다뤄보신 분이라면
problem, you've heard about YOLO even to date.
지금까지도 들어보셨을 것입니다.
Although it's a convolution heavy network today, at least
비록 오늘날에는 여전히 convolution이 많은 network이지만요,
its earlier versions.
적어도 초기 버전은요.
In many even industrial applications,
많은 산업용 application에서도
YOLO is being used as the base for object detection
YOLO는 object detection의 기반으로 사용되고 있습니다,
because it's a fast object detector.
왜냐하면 빠른 object detector이기 때문입니다.
And it's very good in terms of detecting the objects.
그리고 object를 검출하는 데 있어서 매우 뛰어납니다.
What YOLO does I want to very briefly tell you
YOLO가 무엇을 하는지 아주 간략하게
a little bit about.
말씀드리고 싶습니다.
It's basically you look only once in one single pass
기본적으로 이미지를 한 번만(only once) 보고,
on the image.
한 번의 pass로
You generate all of the bounding boxes.
모든 bounding box를 생성합니다.
How it does it is it maps, it divides the image into grid of S
이것이 하는 방식은, 이미지를 S by S grid로 나누는 것입니다,
by S And in this example, it's 7 by 7.
이 예시에서는 7 by 7입니다.
What happens is that for each single box in that grid,
일어나는 일은, grid의 각 개별 box에 대해
it tries to output, it creates a fully convolutional network
그 위치에 object가 있을 확률과 bounding box의
that outputs the probability of an object being
정제(refinement)를 출력하는 fully convolutional network를
in that location, refinements of the bounding boxes.
만든다는 것입니다.
So it generates B bounding boxes, a new hyperparameters,
그래서 새로운 hyperparameter인 B개의
bounding B boxes, that is the refinement of the object that
bounding box를 생성하는데, 이는 그 box에 있는
is present in that box.
object의 정제된 형태입니다.
And also, it generates the class probability, object class
그리고 또한 class probability, 즉 object class
probabilities.
probability도 생성합니다.
And in this case, for example, if it's B equal to 2,
그리고 이 경우, 예를 들어 B가 2라면,
it generates just two bounding boxes
서로 다른 확률을 가진 bounding box를
with different probabilities.
두 개만 생성합니다.
It does this for all of the boxes at the same time.
이것을 모든 box에 대해 동시에 수행합니다.
So basically, it's the same network
그래서 기본적으로, 이 각각의 bounding box에
that is generating something as the output for each
대해 output을 생성하는 것은 동일한 하나의
of these bounding boxes.
network입니다.
And it does generate a number of different options
그리고 이는 object에 대해 여러 다른 옵션을
for the object.
생성합니다.
And as I said, each of those boxes
그리고 말씀드렸듯이,
are associated with a probability.
각 box는 확률 하나와 연관되어 있습니다.
And in this example, the probability
그리고 이 예시에서는
is shown with the weights of the edges in each of those boxes.
각 box에 있는 edge의 굵기로 그 확률을 나타냅니다.
And for these many different bounding boxes and object
그리고 이렇게 많은 서로 다른 bounding box와
probabilities, now we can do thresholding.
object probability에 대해, 이제 thresholding을
And also, there is an algorithm that they use in the paper.
할 수 있습니다. 그리고 논문에서 사용한 알고리즘도 하나 있습니다.
Again, I don't want to go into the details--
다시 말씀드리지만, 세부사항을 파고들고 싶지는 않습니다--
non-maximum suppression, and some algorithms
non-maximum suppression과,
with thresholding involved that identifies the ones that
thresholding을 포함한 몇몇 알고리즘이 가장 확률이
have the highest probabilities.
높은 것들을 식별해줍니다.
So this is a simple implementation or use
이것이 object detection의
of the object detection.
간단한 구현이자 활용 방법입니다.
Again, this is something very useful.
다시 말씀드리지만, 이것은 매우 유용합니다.
If you have time, to spend with the repositories of YOLO.
시간이 있다면 YOLO repository를 살펴보세요.
There are so many different newer versions of YOLO
의학, robotics, 그리고 많은 산업용 application에
that is being used for many applications in medicine,
사용되는 훨씬 더 새로운 버전의 YOLO가 정말 많습니다.
robotics, and also in many industrial applications.
질문은, 이 두 번째 이미지를 어떻게 얻는지,
So the question is, how do we get this second image?
그리고 그 뒤에 있는 직관이 무엇인지에 관한 것이군요.
And what's the intuition behind it?
말씀드렸듯이, 각 grid에 대해
As I said, for each of the grids,
bounding box를 생성합니다.
we generate bounding boxes.
이것에 대해서는 두 개를 생성했고, 다른 모든 것에
For this one, we generated two, for all others,
대해서도 마찬가지로 두 개씩 생성합니다.
we also generate two.
이 B는 다시 말씀드리지만 probability vector이고,
This bee is, again, a probability vector/ and each
각 box는 그 안에 object가 존재할 확률과
of these boxes are associated with probability of existing
연관되어 있습니다.
an object in them.
그리고 모든 patch에 대해 이것들을
And then if I put all of them together for all of the patches,
전부 모으면, 매우 많은 box를 갖게 됩니다.
I have so many boxes.
그리고 각각은 확률 하나와 연관됩니다.
Perfect
좋습니다.
Let's move on.
넘어가겠습니다.
And one of the more recent approaches for object detection
그리고 object detection의 더 최근 접근법 중 하나가
is deter a detection transformer.
DETR, detection transformer입니다.
This is purely based on transformers and the topic
이것은 순수하게 transformer 기반이고,
that we discussed last week.
지난주 우리가 이야기한 주제와
And also I started today, same type
그리고 오늘 제가 시작한 것과 같은 종류의
of self-attention and cross-attention modules
self-attention과 cross-attention module들도
could also generate some object detections and bounding
object detection과 bounding box를 생성할 수 있음을
boxes for us.
보여줍니다.
And how this works?
어떻게 작동할까요?
This is actually not a very old paper,
사실 그렇게 오래된 논문은 아닙니다,
2020, almost five years ago.
2020년, 거의 5년 전이죠.
Although it's now deprecated.
비록 지금은 deprecated 되었지만요.
Nobody uses this for real applications.
실제 application에서는 아무도 이것을 사용하지 않습니다.
But it's a very good example of how
하지만 transformer를 object detection에
to use transformers for object detection.
사용하는 매우 좋은 예시입니다.
And what we do here is basically similar to what
그리고 여기서 우리가 하는 것은 기본적으로 앞서
we've explained earlier.
설명한 것과 비슷합니다.
We may turn the image into patches.
이미지를 patch로 나눕니다.
And then those patches are passed through CNNs
그리고 그 patch들은 CNN을 거쳐
creating a token.
token을 만듭니다.
Then we add positional encoding the same way
그런 다음 제가 patch에 대해 설명했던 것과
that I explained to the patches.
같은 방식으로 positional encoding을 추가합니다.
And those define our tokens for the inputs, which
그리고 그것들이 input에 대한 우리의 token을
are inputs to the transformer encoder, a transformer encoder,
정의하는데, 이는 transformer encoder의 input이 됩니다,
again, a bunch of self-attention layer
다시 말해 여러 개의 self-attention layer,
normalization or any normalization,
normalization,
as well as MLP layers that generates
그리고 MLP layer들로 이루어진 encoder이며,
the output tokens after multiple layers of transformer encoder.
여러 layer의 transformer encoder를 거친 후 output token을 생성합니다.
Then, in order to generate the bounding boxes,
그런 다음, bounding box를 생성하기 위해,
this is the smart part for this algorithm
이 알고리즘에서 영리한 부분은
that it does take the encoder output tokens
encoder output token을
as input in the transformer decoder,
transformer decoder의 input으로 받는다는 것입니다.
but we also define some queries, which
하지만 우리는 또한 몇 개의 query도 정의하는데,
are trainable parameters themselves
이는 그 자체로 trainable parameter입니다.
that each of those, for example, if I add five 5 queries as input
예를 들어 query로 5개, 10개, 20개를
for queries as input, or 10 or 20 queries as input,
input으로 넣는다면,
I'm seeking up to 20 objects to be detected in that image.
그 이미지에서 최대 20개의 object를 검출하려고 하는 것입니다.
And then again, through a combination
그리고 다시, 이 transformer decoder 앞부분의
of self-attention layers in the beginning of this transformer
self-attention layer들의 조합과,
decoder, as well as cross-attention with the encoder
encoder output과의 cross-attention을 통해
So cross-attention and self-attention networks layers,
즉 self-attention과 cross-attention layer를 통해,
it generates the output values for each of these queries, which
각 query에 대한 output 값을 생성하고,
are passed through an FNN, feed forward network,
이것이 FNN, feed forward network를 거쳐
to generate either class labels and the bounding boxes,
class label과 bounding box를 생성하게 됩니다,
very similar to what we discussed earlier, or even
앞서 논의했던 것과 매우 비슷하게요. 혹은
in some cases, it just says there is no object
어떤 경우에는 검출할 object가 없다고
to be detected.
말하기도 합니다.
And at the end, we have the bounding boxes
그리고 마지막에는, output으로 bounding box와
and the classes associated with bounding boxes as the output.
그 bounding box와 연관된 class를 얻게 됩니다.
So the question is, are we inputting every possible box
질문은, 가능한 모든 box를 transformer에 input으로
to the transformer?
넣는지에 관한 것이군요.
No.
아닙니다.
The input here are some triangular parameters
여기 input은 몇몇 learnable parameter로,
that are representing-- they are queries asking
이 input query의 자리에 정말로 object가
the question that I actually want an object to be outwitted
발견되기를 요청하는 query들입니다.
in place of this input query.
그래서 input으로 box나 다른 것이 들어가는 게
So there is no box or anything as the input.
아닙니다.
It's part of the output that it generates the class
class label과 box 좌표를 생성하는 것은
label and the box coordinates.
output의 일부입니다.
So the question is, if the queries are formed in a way
질문은, query가 실제로 우리가 무엇을 찾고 있고
that it actually represents what we want to look for and where
이미지의 어디를 찾아야 하는지를 나타내도록
in the image.
형성되는지에 관한 것이군요.
In this case, what we are looking for
이 경우, 우리가 찾고 있는 것은
is defined by class labels, which are predefined,
미리 정의된 class label들로 정의되고,
and they are as part of the output.
이는 output의 일부입니다.
So our supervision is based on the class labels.
그래서 우리의 supervision은 class label을 기반으로 합니다.
We have a class probability vector.
class probability vector를 가지고 있습니다.
Same way that we defined it for the other algorithms.
다른 알고리즘에서 정의했던 것과 동일한 방식입니다.
So that's how the algorithm knows what type of classes
그래서 이것이 알고리즘이 어떤 종류의 class를
to look for.
찾아야 하는지 아는 방식입니다.
And then in terms of the outputs,
그리고 output 측면에서는,
again, these outputs are supervised.
다시 말씀드리지만, 이 output들도 supervise됩니다.
If you remember based on the L2 norm,
기억하신다면, ground truth box의 L2 loss를
L2 loss of the ground truth boxes.
기반으로 합니다.
We're not telling anything in the query part what to or where
query 부분에서는 어떤 object를 어디서 찾을지에 대해
to look for any of the objects.
아무것도 말해주지 않습니다.
The training, the process itself is back propagating.
학습 과정 자체는 back propagation입니다.
If there are any losses, any errors,
loss나 error가 있으면,
it back propagates the outputs.
output을 통해 back propagate합니다.
So basically, we are not determining anything
그래서 기본적으로, 처음이나 이 부분에서는
in the beginning or in this part.
아무것도 결정하지 않습니다.
So the question was the query is give me up to nine objects.
그래서 질문은 query가 "최대 아홉 개의 object를 달라"는
And yes that's basically what this means.
의미인지에 관한 것이었는데, 네, 기본적으로
And through the self-attention and cross-attention,
그런 의미입니다. 그리고 self-attention과
it will try to generate output tokens that
cross-attention을 통해, FNN 연산을 거쳐
are turned into class and box coordinates
class와 box 좌표로 변환되는 output token을
through that FNN operation.
생성하려고 시도할 것입니다.
Your question is, if the query is over there,
질문은, query가
if they are image patches or not?
image patch인지 아닌지에 관한 것이군요.
No, they are not image patches.
아닙니다, image patch가 아닙니다.
They are just queries for trainable parameters.
그냥 query일 뿐인 trainable parameter입니다.
You put them in to generate the outputs.
output을 생성하기 위해 그것들을 넣습니다.
For each of the inputs, you get the value as the output.
각 input에 대해, 그 값을 output으로 얻습니다.
And that value is turned into class and box coordinates.
그리고 그 값이 class와 box 좌표로 변환됩니다.
Again, the question is, what is object queries?
다시 질문드리자면, object query가 무엇이냐는 것인데,
They are trainable learnable parameters.
이것은 trainable하고 학습 가능한 parameter입니다.
So you initialize them.
그래서 초기화를 하고,
The network finds the best values for them.
network가 그것들에 대한 최적의 값을 찾아냅니다.
And that's what you get as the output.
그리고 그것이 output으로 얻는 것입니다.
The question is, if there is any intuition,
질문은, 어떤 FNN이 어떤 box를 담당하는지에 대한
which FNN gets which box?
직관이 있는지에 관한 것이군요.
The short answer to that is, no, there's nothing
간단히 답하면, 아니요, network가
that stops the network from--
여러 개를 생성하는 것을 막는 것은 아무것도 없습니다--
I mean, we're not including anything
즉, 우리는 network가
that stops the network from generating multiple.
여러 개를 생성하는 것을 막는 것을 포함시키지 않았습니다.
But remember, that there are so many self-attention
하지만 거기에 정말 많은 self-attention과
and cross-attention layers over there
cross-attention layer들이 있다는 것을 기억하세요,
that they are actually interacting with each other
그것들이 실제로 서로 상호작용하면서
and makes each of those queries match
각 query가 output layer 중 하나와
with one of the output layer.
매칭되도록 만듭니다.
So it's not generating the exact same thing as the output.
그래서 output으로 정확히 같은 것을 생성하지는 않습니다.
And we also have control over supervising those FNNs as well.
그리고 우리는 그 FNN들도 supervise하는 제어권을 가지고 있습니다.
So your question is if there are image segmentations, pixel level
질문은, 학습 과정에 image segmentation,
segmentations as part of the training.
즉 pixel level segmentation이 포함되는지에 관한 것이군요.
This algorithm does not require the pixel level segmentations.
이 알고리즘은 pixel level segmentation을 요구하지 않습니다.
It's only supervised based on class labels and bounding boxes.
오직 class label과 bounding box로만 supervise됩니다.
But if you have the pixel level segmentations,
하지만 pixel level segmentation을 가지고 있다면,
you can always turn the pixel level segmentations
언제든 pixel level segmentation을
into a bounding box to train this algorithm,
bounding box로 바꿔서 이 알고리즘을 학습시킬 수 있습니다,
but it doesn't necessarily require that.
하지만 반드시 그것이 필요한 것은 아닙니다.
So the question is, if it's possible to generalize
질문은, 처음 보는(unseen) object에 대해
unseen objects.
일반화가 가능한지에 관한 것이군요.
And by unseen you mean a new class label?
그리고 unseen이라 함은 새로운 class label을
Yes.
의미하는 거죠?
For these types of algorithms that they are fully supervised,
fully supervised인 이런 종류의 알고리즘에서는,
often, there is no way because you are creating
보통 그럴 방법이 없습니다, 왜냐하면
class probability vector.
class probability vector를 만들고 있기 때문입니다.
There is no way of adding something
어떤 다른 class가 있다는 것을
at the end for a new class without previously knowing
미리 알지 못한 상태에서 마지막에 새로운 class를
there is some other classes.
추가할 방법이 없습니다.
So fully supervised networks, often, there is no new object.
그래서 fully supervised network는 보통 새로운 object를
We can have a background object or no object.
다룰 수 없습니다. background object나 no object라는
As you can see, we have the label of no object.
label은 가질 수 있습니다. 보시는 것처럼, no object라는
But there are many algorithms and mixed extensions
label이 있습니다. 하지만 zero-shot learning에 사용되는
of these types of algorithms that are
이런 종류의 알고리즘의
used for zero-shot learning.
많은 혼합 확장(mixed extension)이 있습니다.
Zero shot means understanding finding something new
zero shot이라는 것은, training data에 그런
without having an example of those in the training data.
예시가 없는 상태에서 새로운 것을 찾아내는 것을 의미합니다.
But it's beyond this topic.
하지만 이것은 이 주제를 넘어서는 이야기입니다.
What happens if you have more objects in the scene than what
query로 넣은 것보다 장면에 object가 더 많으면
you put in as the query?
어떻게 되나요?
So that's a great question.
아주 좋은 질문입니다.
It often generates the ones that has the highest confidence
보통 object에 대해 가장 높은 confidence를 가진 것들을,
on the objects, so bounding boxes
즉 confidence가 가장 높은 bounding box를
with the highest confidence.
생성하게 됩니다.
And in those cases, you often want
그리고 그런 경우에는 보통
to add more queries just so you can get more objects.
더 많은 object를 얻기 위해 query를 더 추가하고 싶어집니다.
I'll be here to answer questions,
수업 끝나고 질문이 있으시면
if you have any after the class.
여기 있겠습니다.
But we have a bunch of other topics to cover,
하지만 다뤄야 할 다른 주제들이 아직 많이 남아 있어서,
and I want to make sure we go over them.
그것들을 꼭 살펴보고 넘어가고 싶습니다.
At least you get familiar with the topics.
적어도 그 주제들에 익숙해질 수 있도록요.
So with the object detections, now back
자, object detection은 이 정도로 하고,
to the question I was asked earlier,
아까 받았던 질문으로 돌아가서,
how can we use those types of algorithms
이런 종류의 알고리즘을 instance segmentation에
for instance segmentation?
어떻게 사용할 수 있을까요?
And that's actually not too hard.
사실 그렇게 어렵지 않습니다.
We talked about this when we were
R-CNN 알고리즘에 대해 이야기할 때
talking about R-CNN algorithms, where we run a CNN on the image.
이미 이야기했는데, 이미지에 CNN을 돌리고,
Then we have a region proposal network that
그런 다음 bounding box를 알려주는
gives us the bounding boxes.
region proposal network가 있습니다.
And those bounding boxes are turned into either class labels
그리고 그 bounding box들은 class label과
and bounding box refinements.
bounding box refinement로 변환됩니다.
So this is what we've talked so far with R-CNN and so on.
지금까지 R-CNN 등에 대해 이야기한 내용입니다.
Now, we can turn this into a mask R-CNN
이제 이것을 mask도 생성하는
that also generates the mask.
mask R-CNN으로 바꿀 수 있습니다.
So basically, same architecture that we talked about earlier.
그래서 기본적으로, 앞서 이야기한 것과 동일한
Now, we can take one more output, make it more multitask
architecture입니다. 이제 output을 하나 더 가져와서
and generate the mask predictions.
더 multi-task로 만들고 mask prediction을
So what we used to be doing before was,
생성합니다. 그래서 예전에 하던 것은,
again, image, region proposals, CNN, gives us class label
다시 말씀드리면 이미지, region proposal, CNN을 거쳐서
and the box coordinates.
class label과 box 좌표를 얻는 것이었습니다.
Now, we add another layer of convolution
이제 우리는 pixel level에서
that generates the masks for that object in the pixel level.
그 object에 대한 mask를 생성하는 convolution layer를 하나 더 추가합니다.
And that mask, again, could be the same size
그리고 그 mask는, 다시 말씀드리지만,
as the input and the image, and, basically, on the layer itself.
input이나 이미지와 같은 크기가 될 수 있습니다, layer 자체에서요.
If we use fully convolutional neural networks,
fully convolutional neural network를 사용하면,
that's what we often get as the output.
그것이 흔히 output으로 얻는 것입니다.
For each of the objects, when we have that tiny box,
각 object에 대해, 그 작은 box가 있으면,
we can always get the mask for that.
항상 그것에 대한 mask를 얻을 수 있습니다.
The chair in different settings of the box itself,
서로 다른 box 설정에 있는 의자,
if you have different boxes, the bed and the human,
그리고 침대와 사람,
the baby in the image.
이미지 속 아기까지요.
And this is an extension of the R-CNN algorithm,
이것이 R-CNN 알고리즘의 확장이고,
which we call mask R-CNN.
우리는 이것을 mask R-CNN 이라고 부릅니다.
And with mask R-CNN, the results have been very, very good
그리고 mask R-CNN으로, 우리가 학습시킬 수 있었던
in detecting different objects, different known objects that we
서로 다른, 알려진 object들을 검출하는 데 있어
could train the algorithms for.
매우 매우 좋은 결과를 얻었습니다.
And then there are so many APIs and open source versions
그리고 여러분이 탐색해볼 수 있는 object detector들의
of object detectors that you can explore.
API와 open source 버전들도 아주 많습니다.
There are some links and resources here,
여기 링크와 자료들이 있는데,
but this all, basically, rounds up
이것이 기본적으로 우리가 다루고 싶었던 task들을
and summarizes some of the tasks that we wanted to cover.
전부 정리하고 요약해줍니다.
And they are actually very important for you
그리고 이것들은 여러분이 이 task들을
to understand these tasks.
이해하는 데 정말 중요합니다.
They have been core Computer Vision tasks.
이것들은 core Computer Vision task들이었습니다.
Although these days, Computer Vision is very more advanced.
비록 요즘 Computer Vision은 훨씬 더 발전했지만요.
They are not bound to these tasks.
이런 task들에 얽매여 있지 않습니다.
But if you have industrial applications, for example,
하지만 산업용 application이 있다면, 예를 들어
quality control of separating rotten tomatoes
산업 파이프라인에서 썩은 토마토와 좋은 토마토를
and good tomatoes in an industrial pipeline.
분리하는 품질 관리 같은 경우라면요.
Then with Computer Vision, you need
Computer Vision으로, object를 검출한 다음
to be able to detect objects and then
그것을 좋은 것과 나쁜 것으로
classify them into good or bad.
분류할 수 있어야 합니다.
That's why it's important to still understand and know
그래서 이런 단계와 파이프라인을 이해하고
these steps and pipelines and how to do them in real time.
실시간으로 어떻게 수행하는지 아는 것이 여전히 중요합니다.
But now, there are larger scale models
하지만 이제는 여러분 모두 익숙한
that you are all familiar with.
더 큰 규모의 model들이 있죠.
This summarizes the first part, the Computer Vision tasks
이것으로 첫 번째 부분, 즉 제가 이야기하고 싶었던
that I wanted to talk about.
Computer Vision task들을 요약했습니다.
And the last piece that I want to spend 10 minutes on
그리고 마지막으로 10분 정도 할애하고 싶은 주제는
is around visualization and understanding.
visualization과 understanding에 관한 것입니다.
Again, this has been a big lecture by itself.
다시 말씀드리지만, 이것 자체만으로도 강의 하나가 될 만큼 큰 주제입니다.
And in 2050, 60, until 2020s that the topic of computer
그리고 2050, 60년대까지-- 아니 2020년대,
and even before that 2014, '13 the topic of visualizing neural
그리고 그 이전인 2014년, '13년까지도, neural network를
networks has been very hot and very much--
visualize하는 주제는 매우 뜨거웠고 아주--
it helped us gain understanding into what
network가 무엇을 학습하고 있는지에 대한
the networks are learning.
이해를 얻는 데 도움이 되었습니다.
And I'm going to summarize some of those,
그리고 저는 그 중
the most important ones here that you may need
여러분이 application에서 사용해야 할 수도 있는
to use in your applications.
가장 중요한 것들을 요약해드리겠습니다.
But before that, let me go back to the linear classifier
하지만 그 전에, 우리가 이야기했던 linear classifier로
that we talked about.
다시 돌아가 보겠습니다.
We spent quite a lot of time on linear classifiers.
linear classifier에 꽤 많은 시간을 들였었죠.
And with the linear classifiers, what we did was at the end,
그리고 linear classifier에서 우리가 한 것은, 결국
we said, if I look at the linear function, what the network is
linear function을 보면, network가 학습하고 있는 것을
learning, I can have a template for each of those classes.
각 class에 대한 template로 가질 수 있다는 것이었습니다.
Like for example, for this car, you
예를 들어, 이 자동차의 경우
can always see a front facing car as a template.
정면을 향한 자동차를 template로 항상 볼 수 있습니다.
We can do the same with neural networks.
neural network에서도 동일하게 할 수 있습니다.
If I visualize one of the filters,
filter 중 하나를 visualize한다면,
so here, we visualize the weights of the linear function.
여기서 우리는 linear function의 weight를 visualize했습니다.
It was the visual viewpoint.
그것이 시각적인 관점이었죠.
I can do the same with linear--
저는 linear를 visualize하는 것과--
sorry with visualizing the filters in the neural networks.
아니, neural network의 filter를 visualize하는 것도 동일하게
So for each of the filters, the network
할 수 있습니다. 그래서 각 filter에 대해,
is, for example, is learning something that is basically
network는 예를 들어 여기 보시는 것처럼 기본적인
some of the basic shapes, orientations, or simple shapes,
모양, 방향, 혹은 단순한 형태 같은 것을
as you can see here.
학습하고 있습니다.
Although this visualization, we can only do it for the layers
비록 이 visualization은 channel이 적은 layer에
that we have few channels.
대해서만 할 수 있지만요. 예를 들어 channel이
Like, for example, if we have three channels,
3개라면, RGB 이미지에 넣어서
I can put them in an RGB image and just visualize it.
그냥 visualize할 수 있습니다.
But as you remember, in CNNs, that was not the case.
하지만 기억하시다시피, CNN에서는 그렇지 않았죠.
In CNNs, we had different sometimes quite a few channels
CNN에서는 중간 layer에 때때로 상당히 많은
in the middle layer, so it's not easy to visualize those
channel이 있어서, 그것들을 우리가 볼 수 있는
in something that we can see.
형태로 visualize하기가 쉽지 않습니다.
But that's what you basically see.
하지만 기본적으로 보시는 것이 그것입니다.
In earlier layers that we have fewer channels,
channel이 적은 초반 layer에서는,
we can visualize them and see the network is actually
network가 실제로 어떤 패턴을 학습하고 있는 것을
learning some patterns.
visualize해서 볼 수 있습니다.
So it starts learning patterns.
그래서 패턴을 학습하기 시작하는 것입니다.
And then later stages, it gets more holistic and bigger
그리고 이후 단계로 갈수록, 더 전체적이고(holistic) 큰
patterns as if we train--
패턴을 갖게 됩니다, 만약 우리가--
sorry, if we run something that we call guided back propagation,
아니, 우리가 guided back propagation이라고 부르는 것을 실행하면,
we can also visualize those, but not as simple as this.
그것들도 visualize할 수 있지만, 이만큼 간단하지는 않습니다.
I want to highlight a couple of ways
neural network를
of understanding and visualizing the neural networks, which
이해하고 visualize하는 몇 가지 방법을 강조하고 싶습니다,
are actually important.
정말 중요한 것들이거든요.
One is the concept of saliency.
그 중 하나가 바로 saliency라는 개념입니다.
So in many applications, it's very important for you
많은 application에서 어떤 pixel이
to know which pixel matters.
중요한지 아는 것이 매우 중요합니다.
For example, in a medical application,
예를 들어, medical application에서
when you do a classification of tumor versus none,
tumor인지 아닌지를 classification할 때,
you want to see which parts of that image
이미지의 어느 부분이 실제로 tumor인지
is actually the tumor.
보고 싶으실 겁니다.
Because if you want to automate this,
왜냐하면 이것을 자동화하고 싶다면,
nobody cares about knowing if there is tumor or not.
tumor가 있는지 없는지 아는 것에는 아무도 관심이 없기 때문입니다.
Everybody cares about where in the image the tumor is.
모두가 이미지의 어디에 tumor가 있는지에 관심이 있습니다.
So in order to do that, simplest application
그렇게 하기 위한 가장 간단한 application은,
is we train a network, a feedforward neural network that
값이나 class label '개'를 생성하는
generates the value or the class label doc.
feedforward neural network를 학습시키는 것입니다.
But what we can do is we can--
하지만 우리가 할 수 있는 것은--
actually, before I showed you that, in this case,
사실, 그것을 보여드리기 전에, 이 경우
in order to train this network, what we've done was
이 network를 학습시키기 위해 우리가 했던 것은
we always took the derivative of the neural network, the weights,
항상 weight에 대한 neural network의 미분,
sorry, of the loss or of the class score with respect
아니, weight를 update하기 위해 loss나 class score의
to the weights in order to update the weights.
weight에 대한 미분을 가져오는 것이었습니다.
Now, what I need is for each pixel,
이제 제가 필요한 것은, 각 pixel에 대해
I want to see how much changing the pixel value
pixel 값을 변경하는 것이
would affect the dog score?
dog score에 얼마나 영향을 미치는지 보고 싶습니다.
What does this mean?
이것이 무슨 의미일까요?
What I explained is the meaning of the variation.
제가 방금 설명한 것은 변화량(variation)의 의미입니다.
So this means that the meaning of basically gradient.
즉 이것은 기본적으로 gradient의 의미입니다.
So if I take the gradient of the score with respect
그래서 network weight가 아니라
to now the pixel values, not the network weights
이제 pixel 값에 대한 score의 gradient를 취하면,
anymore, with pixel values, I can visualize those gradients.
그 gradient들을 visualize할 수 있습니다.
And visualizing those means that these
그리고 그것들을 visualize한다는 것은
are the pixels that matter.
바로 이 pixel들이 중요한 pixel이라는 뜻입니다.
In order to classify dog on this image,
이 이미지에서 개를 분류하기 위해서는,
those are the pixels that matter.
바로 그 pixel들이 중요합니다.
So if I change the values of those pixels,
그래서 그 pixel들의 값을 바꾸면,
the dog score will be changed.
dog score가 바뀌게 됩니다.
Again, this is the basic meaning and definition of gradients
다시 말씀드리지만, 이것이 우리가 이야기했던 gradient의
that we've talked about.
기본적인 의미이자 정의입니다.
So this is one way.
그래서 이것이 한 가지 방법입니다.
If you run this on different objects
network를 학습시킨
that you've trained in the network,
서로 다른 object들에 대해 이것을 실행하면,
then this is what you get.
이렇게 얻게 됩니다.
So that's one way of understanding saliency.
이것이 saliency를 이해하는 한 가지 방법입니다.
And it's very effective in many cases.
그리고 많은 경우에 매우 효과적입니다.
But sometimes it's not just about the pixel values
하지만 때로는 끝까지 가는 pixel 값에
all the way to the back.
관한 것만이 아닙니다.
You want to see for each of the classes
각 class에 대해 activation이 어떻게 작동하는지
how the activations work.
보고 싶으실 겁니다.
And this brings us to class activation maps
그리고 이것이 우리를 class activation map,
or CAM algorithm, class activation mapping, CAM
즉 CAM 알고리즘, class activation mapping, CAM이나
or Grad-CAM that I'll talk about in two minutes,
제가 2분 후에 이야기할 Grad-CAM으로 이끕니다.
are one of the most and widely used
이것들은 CNN을 이해하는 데
algorithms for understanding CNNs,
가장 널리 사용되는 알고리즘 중 하나이고,
and also could be used for other architectures too.
다른 architecture에도 사용될 수 있습니다.
But for transformers, we have a much better way
하지만 transformer의 경우, 이를 이해하는
of making sense of those, which actually we
훨씬 더 나은 방법이 있는데, 사실 지난
talked in the last lecture.
강의에서 이야기했었습니다.
So what happens is that for each of the convolution layers,
일어나는 일은, 각 convolution layer마다
we often do pooling.
흔히 pooling을 합니다.
And the pooling generates feature maps.
그리고 pooling은 feature map을 생성합니다.
The feature maps are then turned into scores.
feature map은 다시 score로 변환됩니다.
And those scores with those values of the weights.
그리고 그 score들은 weight 값들과 함께요.
If we extend the math, basically, we simply
수식을 확장해보면, 기본적으로 class score를
can highlight the class scores in a weighted sum form.
weighted sum 형태로 간단히 강조할 수 있습니다.
And this means that we can trace back class predictions
그리고 이는 우리가 class prediction을 다시 feature map까지,
all the way back to the feature maps
그리고 공간의 특정 위치까지 거슬러 올라가서
and in specific locations of the space,
추적할 수 있다는 것을 의미합니다, 왜냐하면
because convolution layers are always
convolution layer들은 항상 이미지 공간에
mapped to a space in the image space two.
매핑되기 때문입니다.
We do convolution as the spatial consistency across all
우리는 convolution을 하기 때문에, 모든 연산에 걸친
of the operations can help us trace back
spatial 일관성이 우리가 이미지 공간까지
all the way to the image space.
거슬러 올라가는 데 도움을 줄 수 있습니다.
So anyways, we can look at the feature maps
어쨌든, feature map을 살펴보고
and see how the class activations,
class activation이, 즉 이 각각의 class들이
each of these classes are actually
실제로 이미지 속
impacting those locations in the image.
어떤 위치에 영향을 미치는지 볼 수 있습니다.
And with that now, if I do this multiplication of weights
그리고 그렇게, 만약 학습된 weight를
versus the weights that we've learned
feature 값 위에서
on top of the feature values, we create some class activations.
곱하면, class activation을 만들어낼 수 있습니다.
And this means that I have a way now to go back to the image
그리고 이는 이제 다시 이미지 공간으로 돌아갈 방법이
space, because as long as I'm in the convolution space,
있다는 뜻입니다, convolution 공간에 있는 한
I can go all the way back to the image
이미지까지 계속 거슬러 올라갈 수 있으니까요.
and create these maps of, for example, for each of the classes
그래서 예를 들어 palace, dome, church, altar,
palace, dome, church, altar, and monastery,
monastery 각 class에 대한
we can have different class activation maps.
이런 map을 만들 수 있습니다.
These are the weights.
이것이 weight입니다.
These are the pixels or areas of the convolution layer
이것들은 이 특정 class들에 대한 score를
that have been driving the scores
이끌어낸 convolution layer의 pixel이나 영역입니다.
It's the same for others, like class activation maps
다른 것들도 마찬가지입니다, 서로 다른 이미지에서
for one single object in different images.
동일한 하나의 object에 대한 class activation map처럼요.
But there is a problem with this.
하지만 여기에는 문제가 있습니다.
And that problem is that we can only
그 문제는, 우리가 이것을
apply this to the last convolution layer,
마지막 convolution layer에만 적용할 수 있다는 것입니다,
because this is the only way we can do it.
왜냐하면 우리가 할 수 있는 방법이 그것뿐이기 때문입니다.
We can only go to the last convolution layer.
마지막 convolution layer까지만 갈 수 있습니다,
The way that we did the calculations here.
여기서 계산을 한 방식대로요.
And in order to solve that problem,
그리고 그 문제를 해결하기 위해,
there is one variant of the algorithm
Grad-CAM이라고 불리는
called Grad-CAM, so gradient-weighted class
알고리즘의 한 변형이 있습니다, 즉 gradient-weighted
activation maps.
class activation map입니다.
It's basically the same algorithm.
기본적으로 동일한 알고리즘입니다.
We need to weight calculate the weights with respect to the--
우리는 weight를 계산해야 하는데, 그 기준은--
we basically take one of the layers
기본적으로 어떤 activation을 만든
that created some activation.
layer 하나를 가져옵니다.
In the class level, we compute the gradients,
class 수준에서, 우리는 gradient를 계산합니다,
instead of just calculating the multiplication between W
W와 feature 사이의 곱셈만 계산하는 대신,
We go all the way back with the gradients
gradient를 이용해 끝까지 거슬러 올라가서
and create a weight based on the gradients,
gradient를 기반으로 weight를 만들고,
and then that is used instead of the weights,
그것을 weight 대신 사용합니다,
it's aggregate of all of the weights
그 특정 layer까지의 모든 weight와
and gradients up to that specific layer.
gradient를 집계(aggregate)한 것입니다.
And then we weight that with that.
그리고 그것으로 weight를 매깁니다.
And then we also use ReLU to pass the positive ones.
그리고 양수인 것들만 통과시키기 위해 ReLU도 사용합니다.
And then that could also be all the way
그러면 그것도 이미지 공간에서 전부
shown in the image space.
보여줄 수 있습니다.
So I talked about CAM, which was only applied
그래서 저는 CAM에 대해 이야기했는데, 이는 마지막
to the last convolution layer.
convolution layer에만 적용되는 것이었습니다.
If you want to--
만약 여러분이 원한다면--
but this is not possible because in most of the CNN algorithms,
하지만 이것은 불가능한데, 왜냐하면 대부분의 CNN 알고리즘에서
we don't have just one convolution layer at the end.
마지막에 convolution layer 하나만 있는 게 아니기 때문입니다.
We always have some operations fully connected and so on.
항상 fully connected 등의 연산이 있습니다.
So in order to be able to carry this class activation
그래서 이 class activation을 convolution layer까지
to the convolution layer, if there
전달할 수 있도록 하기 위해, 중간에 다른 것이
is something else in the middle, we often use the gradients
있다면, 흔히 gradient를 사용해서
and basically weigh the maps with the gradients aggregates.
기본적으로 gradient 집계값으로 map에 가중치를 줍니다.
And then we can actually do the visualization.
그러면 실제로 visualization을 할 수 있습니다.
They create these heat maps for each of the objects.
각 object에 대해 이런 heat map을 만들어냅니다.
So this was about CNNs.
이것이 CNN에 관한 이야기였습니다.
But we talked about transformers last week in the last lecture
하지만 지난주 마지막 강의에서 이야기했던
that they inherently come with the activation maps.
transformer는 본질적으로 activation map을 함께 갖고 있습니다.
Do you remember that language matrix
Justin이 보여줬던 language matrix를 기억하시나요,
that Justin showed, that for each of the output words,
각 output word마다
there is a tension weight for the input.
input에 대한 attention weight가 있었죠.
We can do that, the same thing for the pixels.
pixel에 대해서도 동일한 것을 할 수 있습니다.
For each of the outputs, we can create these maps
각 output에 대해, pixel 공간에서
in the pixel space and visualize the features of the ViTs
이런 map을 만들어서 ViT의 feature를 pixel 공간에서
in the pixel space.
visualize할 수 있습니다.
So basically, with ViTs and transformers,
그래서 기본적으로 ViT와 transformer에서는
this is much easier.
이것이 훨씬 더 쉽습니다.
We already have a way to visualize
attention, weight를 visualize할 방법이
the attentions, the weights.
이미 마련되어 있습니다.
But with CNNs, we often use Grad-CAM
하지만 CNN에서는 흔히 Grad-CAM이나
or these types of algorithms.
이런 종류의 알고리즘을 사용합니다.
That said, I did this task that I
자, 오늘 다루고 싶었던 주제들을 다 마칠 수
thought I wouldn't be able to, completing the topics I
없을 것 같았는데, 다행히 이렇게
wanted to talk about today.
끝낼 수 있었네요.
And next session, we'll have the lecture
다음 시간에는 video understanding에 관한
around video understanding.
강의를 하겠습니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.